welcome everyone it's great to be here
again and sorry sorry minor glitch there
it's wonderful to be here again and
we're this is a the fourth QA and I've
deeply appreciated the previous ones and
so let's let's get to the questions
right away so we can get as many in as
possible in our limited time and so the
first question is from patreon supporter
Mykel thank you Mike for your support I
hope that you'll find my answer to
question helpful so you are you asked
the question since yeah Sam Harris does
advocate spiritual practice why do you
lump him in with those with a purely
materialistic reductionist worldview so
that's a good question I don't know if
I've ever explicitly put Sam Harris in a
metaphysical category I usually put him
in a category of more of an
epistemological category that he strikes
I think more clearly which is he
represents himself as as a proponent of
rationality and so I have some
criticisms of that I think his model of
rationality is too narrow I won't make
that argument in detail here it's
something that in fact the next few
episodes in the series are trying to
address I don't I'm not blaming Sam
Harris of this in particular I think
it's rather he's symptomatic of a too
narrow conception of rationality to put
it very briefly our culture has tended
to conflate rationality either with
intelligence on one side or with logic
allottee on the other and I'm gonna try
and argue and show you so I'm sorry this
is promise Airy why those are inadequate
now why I think I might I might infer
but I don't know I'm not I'm not
claiming that I have any direct a
coating quoted evidence to this
but what I might I might infer that he's
in a form of reductive physicalism is
because of some of the things he talks
about with respect to phenomena like
free will and and whatnot I also share
with Sam Harris that and some of you've
heard this that I I'm I generally can I
consider myself a compiled list and that
I think many notions of free will as
that we somehow possess without us an
unmoved mover don't ultimately make
sense to me so that's an epistemic
criticism but they also I'm not quite
sure what people are wanting let me just
step aside from answering the Sam Harris
questions to say this I this is a
genuine question this is not me this is
not me being sly I I want to enter into
a dialogue with people who can give me a
clear precise oratory maybe that's too
stringent I shouldn't hold people to a
standard that I myself cannot me but at
least I make that the clearest possible
explanation of what it is they feel they
would be losing if they lost if they
found out for sure that their notion of
free will was false and this is not a
trick question I'm not trying to do
something rhetorical or sly I want to
get like what would be the
phenomenological difference what is the
fear what is the concern and so that's
how I want to address the issue of
people I want to get into a deeper
discussion with people about it I've
already said in earlier episodes what I
why I don't they don't agree with it
that being L said let's return back to
sam harris because this is a different
point this is not on the issue about
whether or not freewill is a true or
false claim it's that under what I'm
saying is based on what he said about
that what he has to say about atheism
and what he has to say about being able
to read sort of moral principles off the
scientific worldview I'm concluding that
he has a pretty reductionist
coolest approach let me now take the
time to again point out to people that
there are many brands of physicalism and
there's a it's there's a considerable
and important philosophical difference
and this is something I teach the
university courses and many people have
been arguing for and jerry fodor way
back in the 80s was arguing for this
very deeply there's a big and important
philosophical difference between
reductive physicalism and non reductive
physicalism a reductive physicalist of
things that ultimately the talk about
right that all other levels at which we
talk will be ultimately completely
reduced to the language of physics so
this is the idea that the way in which
we really we've come to realize that
lightning is just and nothing more than
electricity
we will be able to show that you know
the mind or consciousness is nothing but
brain behavior a quick reason why many
non-physical lists like myself who
reject that idea let's not do
consciousness because that that's a vast
problem let's do one that I think is
more amenable just for the purposes of
discussion here I don't think
intelligence is identifiable reducible
to a brain state in the sense that
intelligence is nothing but or just or
only a brain state here is why because I
believe that artificial intelligence is
a real thing and it is going to become
even more and more like our intelligence
and the machines that are generating
artificial intelligence do not have
organized or Ganic brains like mine they
do not they are made out of different
components organized differently
spatially they don't have to have the
metabolism that I have etc etc etc that
means intelligence is what is called in
the philosophical literature multiplied
realizable the same intelligence can be
implemented in a physical system
physical system that has the organic
mush in my head called the brain but it
could be implemented in this physical
system in front of me right now a
computer
right and so therefore trying to reduce
intelligence to a particular material
set of properties one specific set is a
mistake here's another thing that is
multiple e realizable evolution is
another thing that is multiple e
realizable erosion here's another thing
that's multiple realizable combustion
these are all things that you can't say
that combustion is identical with the
particular state of wood and oxygen
because other things other than wood
combust etc that being said many people
who are non non reductive physicalists
like myself want to talk about right
what what is the nature of these
higher-order patterns like intelligent
and erosion and evolution and the idea
is well sorry I that sorry that was
being presumptuous on my part many
people would argue that these patterns
are these higher-level patterns are real
patterns and here's my basic argument in
a nutshell for why that's the case all
of the information that I use in order
to make inferences about the bottom
level at the level of the particles the
particles are identical the forces are
identical all of the difference that
makes all of the information by which
the science is possible is at this level
it has to be real or the science isn't
real and then the inferences about
reality are not based on real patterns
of real information that strikes me and
other people to as implausible now why
is this so physicalism then why isn't
there some kind of Platonism or
something like that the idea is that
these higher-level patterns are
nevertheless right part of can be
understood as consistent with the
entities properties processes of physics
it's not that they've that they are so
let's let's go back to it let's go back
to
erosion erosion can't be reduced to
what's happening in this particular kind
of clay just like combustion can't be
reduced to a particular state in wood
but notice you what you never get you
never get erosion that isn't physical in
some sense you never get well free of
any you know clay or dirt or rock
there's erosion that doesn't happen see
multiple e realizable means it is not
reducible to any fit you know particular
physical medium but it also demonstrates
for the similar argument that it's not
independent from it it's so it's much
more more closer in that sense to an
Aristotelian view than a platonic view
so that is why I tend to be very
suspicious of people who seem to talk as
if everything beyond a certain simple
I'm trying not to be insulting to her so
I'm really trying not to be but a
certain simple physicalist ontology
right that's why I are resistant or I'm
proposing a very rich physicalism and
therefore I'm very critical of people
like again I'm concluding and I'm
willing to acknowledge of my inference
is wrong if people provide me with good
textual evidence but I'm concluding I'm
surmising that he seems to be committed
to something very much like a reductive
physicalism that being said I think the
fact that he is talking about spiritual
practices is very important I also am
concerned I guess I have concern about
how those spiritual practices reveal
something about reality and are not just
ways in which we're modifying cognition
and consciousness that we find sort of
personally
beneficial see one of the things that
one of the things that I would emphasize
that is available to you if when you're
a non reductive or non reductive
physicalist is that you have real
relations like when I talk about when I
talk about
the transgender relationship between the
agents and arena and so I think
spiritual exercises don't just right
transform how we are present to reality
they transform how reality can be
disclosed and presented to us and so I
think in that sense what I've seen him
say again I'm open to talking to him or
talking to people who are talking on his
behalf as as long as it's a you know a
fair discussion um I think his model of
spiritual practices tends to be very
unipolar so all of these things sort of
sit together in my mind as more than
impressions they're their conclusions
I've drawn I think he has a very
truncated notion of rationality which
makes it very problematic for him to
deal with metaphor and symbol I think in
some in some important ways I think his
again drawing a conclusion I think that
here he seems to be advocating a kind of
reductive physicalism a kind of what's
called the identity theory and giving
you reasons why I find that deeply
problematic and then I think his
advocacy of spiritual practices well I
appreciate him doing this especially
with the influence he wields I am
concerned that is very unique Oller it's
only talking from right the
transformation of consciousness and
cognition and not how there's alteration
transformation of the way reality can be
disclosed to us and I think that's
crucial because for me the capacity for
an agog II is central to - to a more
rich understanding of spirituality my
final criticism of Harris is I I would
like to see him being more self-critical
I would like him to be more so I've
tried to demonstrate that in my own
series one of the things I'll do for
example
I'm going to do it shortly as I'll
present the theory of the carbon
scientific theory of wisdom that myself
and Leo Ferraro published in 2013 and
then subjected to criticism that
capacity for self criticism and that
that's what that work is not very old
right but the capacity for genuine self
criticism is I think something that
bespeaks to me you know a good scientist
a good thinker so I would like I would
like to see that more in Harris's
interactions so for all of those reasons
that I tent that's why I tend to sort I
guess what was the verb I tend to lump
him in with that no like I said I try to
indicate where some of them I'm more
confident in my criticism out his view
of rationality and then others were on
drawing conjecture I'm drawing it I'm
drawing a conclusion an interpretive
conclusion from some of the some of his
work that I've read in some of the
arguments I've seen so that abet Mike I
hope that answers your question let's
move to the next question so this is
from a patreon supporter thank you again
for your support
Mackenzie Levitt what do you think about
the idea that what people call spiritual
entities are imaginative and intuitive
personifications of certain patterns of
being could this offer a new way to
understand religious expressions like
the Spirit of Christ lives within us so
I think that that there I am in broad
agreement with the intent and the spirit
of this question the idea that some of
the terms we use are personifications
there are ways of bringing the machinery
by which we relate to people into play
so that we can get access to patterns
that are very difficult for us this is
not identical to but I think it's
consonant with an argument that Paul van
der clay has made and I want to talk to
Paul again about it where he thinks that
the best way in which we have to
approach certain realities is what
Pascal calls a spirit of finesse where
we're bringing in much more of our
perspectival and procedural and
participate
skills and and that the best way to
trigger and activate the finesse we need
to deal with some very complex aspects
reality is through taking a stance that
God is personal I'm not clear if Paul is
ultimately advocating that God belongs
properly to the category persons or if
that's a form of personification or if
he's trying to say something between
those two so I'll leave Paul to address
that point I don't want to startle him
with anything what I would say in that
is we got we have I think some very good
argument clear evidence also that
certain ways of activating our our
cognition put us into the correct
pattern of processing in our brain so
that we can couple to and pick up on
some of the more complex patterns in the
world let me give you an example or
elysia your arrow and dynamics and
actions argues that when we move into a
narrative way of thinking that gets our
minds organizing in this highly
multi-layered self-organizing referring
forward and backward multi-layer so you
get this highly complex way of
processing information it's a very very
much put you into the correct pattern of
processing your cognition for picking up
on dynamical systems in the environment
you as narrative helps put your mind
into the frame that couples best with
dynamical systems in the environment
which is why stories although we have to
be taught them they're not natural to us
this is something I want to talk to Paul
to again when he talks about it being on
the machine code a little bit worried
about that way of talking about it
because of Daniel whose work that we
have to really practice and practice and
practice and for a long development tool
arc before we get narrative but let's go
back to the point it's it's so I'm
personifying right now if I understand
that word correctly and then I'm seeing
what's happening around me as a story
because there's a complex dynamical
system in companying in
environment and write the narrative
helps meet couple to it now do i
thinking that it's actually a narrative
running sort of in the physics of this
room no not at all
not at all but do I think that the
narrative way of thinking might be
indispensable for me actually coupling
to these write patterns you bet so you
can watch exhaustion hunters these are
people who hunt animals by basically
running them down they're some of the
very few hundred gather groups that are
left and what they do is they they track
the animal then they hunt the animal
down by humans have a tremendous
capacity for marathon running and using
their either you know frontal lobes to
track science and what they do is they
just keep chasing the animal until it
heat exhaustion then they're capable of
killing it it seems to be a very
prevalent hunter-gatherer strategy by
the way obviously it's not going to work
in some environments but now what's
interesting is at certain points they
you that the hunters leo Ferraro I've
seen a version of this and then Leo
Ferraro referred me to another version
of this a documentary film on yes though
they'll come to a point where they've
lost the animal and you most of I would
most of us would you say okay when you
look for signs on the other you know
what they do they do things like they
hunched over and they try to imitate the
animal so what they're doing is they're
getting into this again they're turning
their cognition into a particular
they're trying to get the perspective
all knowing and they're trying to get
into the agent or really in a
relationship of the animal and when they
do that then they go oh it went that way
and then they track the animal and then
they come back to a point where they can
find the signs and they can they can you
know they can then see the antelope for
example that they're tracking so I think
very often what religious symbols do is
they exact cognate cognitive processes
so that they can then be used to put us
into a frame of processing that
genuinely Couples us in a real
relationship to real patterns in the
world so that the
world is disclosing itself to us in ways
that it couldn't do before so if if
that's what this the term the terms the
Spirit of Christ living within us are
doing gay eating people access for
example to putting them into a frame of
processing that allows them to access
and respond to and exact aspects of
their own embodied and often unconscious
cognition then I see myself in agreement
with the idea that these are
personifications the problem we face and
this is why I've taken so long to answer
this question and again this harkens
back to some of the criticisms I have of
Harris is when we hear personification
and when we hear metaphor we hear
ornamentation we hear dispensable
frilliness that's added on just for some
sort of aesthetic aspect and that is not
what I'm arguing for what I'm arguing
for here is something that is deeply
powerful it activates us and puts us
into a direct perspectival procedural
and participatory relationship with real
patterns in the world are these things
literal no but what you got to get
between this literal and therefore it's
real and metaphor and therefore it's
just ornamental that's why I've tried to
work so hard on this notion of the trans
Jack the transgender so I hope that
answers your question and I think this
is this is a this is an issue that a lot
of people are talking about and I hope
you consider other voices in this of
course I've already mentioned Paul Van
der clays talking about this I
Jonathan page always doing some of the
most important work on YouTube in my
opinion on the whole topic of symbolism
Christopher Master Pietro and I did some
discussions about our work on symbolism
I think part of what is emerging in this
sort of the sense that people are having
that we're we're in this Kairos this
cusp in
cultural change is we're trying to get
outside of a literalism and a
fundamentalism without just slipping
into well it's it's just it's merely a
metaphor and so that's where I'll leave
that question that's one question
very provocative very thought-provoking
thank you very much for so the next
question is from patreon Felix Felix
thank you for your fantastic and helpful
work you're welcome and thank you for
your support and your encouragement
every time I get this it's it's helpful
and meaningful to me every single time I
need this encouragement
I'm very value it thank you much
as I understand it you are materialist
yeah one of your favorite philosophers
is Plato that's for sure
how do you square plato's idealism with
your own materialism to put it another
way how does an acog expiring function
of materialist that is one-world
universe so again this is the issue
about what it means to say one world if
as I've argued when is a non reductive
materialist it makes sense to talk about
emergent levels layers of reality that
have properties that the Constituent
levels don't have some of you want to
see this idea developed in more detail
please take a look at some of the
discussions I had with JP more so and
we'll have another one soon when I
talked about the deep continuity
hypothesis in contrast to his pen
psychism
and so how I would understand
Plato within a non reductive physicalist
framework in which an agog expiring
still makes sense is the following by
the way one Apollo's and say it's a
fantastic question I should have I want
to apologize because I should have
directly addressed this question at some
point in this series and I don't think I
did so I thank you for the opportunity
to address this telling with
you know but here's what I would say I
would say that when Plato is talking
about the I dos and I've already argued
this is this is the structural
functional organization it's also
patterns of intelligibility so I think
for example that your evolution or
erosion also have patterns of
intelligibility there are real patterns
the structural functional organization
their structural functional organization
that makes them be also is what allows
that to be right intelligible to me I've
gone over that in this series so I'm not
going to press on that point too much
and so what I get from
platonist is notion of an acog a is that
as you know things especially when we're
talking about the procedural
participatory knowing there's a there's
a deep conformity and so as my cognition
becomes related to different patterns of
intelligibility different levels or
layers of reality different aspects of
reality will be disclosed to me let's
pay attention to what that means
hydrogen and oxygen are not right liquid
there but water is water has properties
and powers that hydrogen and oxygen
don't have now water is it made out of
dead elves it's still physical because
there's a story sorry that's the wrong
word I should be more careful forgive me
there's a explanation of how the
hydrogen and the oxygen work together to
produce a structural functional
organization which is real and has
causal properties that are real in the
way or it interacts with other things
that have other structural functional
organizations so as I am able to couple
two different pattern levels of reality
different patterns of intelligibility
and also gaining access to different
causal powers and properties of reality
and that is also calling forth from me
different powers and properties we
in my cognition and that's how the onic
and agog a can flow so I want to remind
you that many of the people who were
responsible for the Scientific
Revolution of the earlier 20th century
both the cosmic relativistic and the
quantum are deeply influenced by
Neoplatonism John Spencer does this in
his book called the internal law he
argues this this but the neoplatonism
didn't we'll need them to posit a two
world or to abandon their their
commitment to physicalism but of course
what it does show and look look at look
at look at look at look at the deep
divide between relativity and quantum
mechanics if there's anything that tells
us that our model of the world is later
is that the attempts to you know get
these to reconcile together our show are
proving to be very very difficult the
relationship to I I predict the
relationship is going to turn out to be
very complex just like the control the
relationship between being a living
thing and being in organic chemicals of
organizing and autopoietic and dynamic
and developmental we had to go to all of
these conceptual innovations before we
could see how life was a physical thing
but that doesn't mean that life isn't a
nerd thing okay so I think that it's
possible I try to give you some ways of
understanding of both to practice
science and also to practice sort of a
platonic spirituality of an agog a in
which you can reconcile a platonic I
guess a platonic view I don't think it's
I don't think you should call what Plato
has a theory of the forms I don't think
that's quite right but anyways that's
another question that you can reconcile
the Platonic view with a non reductive
physicalism so I think that the deep
continuity hypothesis the idea that
there's a deep continuity between things
that are self-organizing and things that
are autopoietic lee living and that
there's a deep continuity between
autopoietic things and thing
that are intelligent cognitive things
and then there's a deep continuity
between cognitive things and rational
beings and so forth that that deep
continuity gives us something very
analogous to what Platina has had but
with you know the great chain of being
the levels of reality that a person
moves through in an agog a what does
deep continuity mean deep continuity
means what I've been arguing for it's
not my idea it's Evan Thompson's idea
developed from Francisco Braille deep
contnue it is to say there is just like
there that the some of the core
principles in the structural functional
organization of self of self organizing
things are taken out and expanded upon
in autopoietic things and then some of
the principles of biological
organization are taken out and and it
developed exact it into cognition I've
tried to show you what I think is a
version of this in how are the bio
economic principles of our embody brains
are exactly up into constraining
information processing and making us
intelligent cognitive agents that's a
non reductive physicalism and there's a
way in which their reality is really
layered and there's a way of course in
which as I've just shown to exaptation
we can anagogical e assent but as I said
before this is not just an ascension
within this is a point that I get from
Eric pearl right and I tried to do with
the broader example as there's
exaptation within my cognition
there's also disclosing of powers and
properties within the different levels
of reality that was an excellent
question so I wanted to take a lot of
time to try and give you my best take on
it so the next question is from a
patreon supporter thank you and it's
McKenzie Levitt could you say what your
favorite genre of music is and why
favorite genre of music that's a tough
one
I suppose you know you sort of the
desert island tested if I could only
listen to one kind of when Jean rock
music on a desert island would probably
be classical music calm and mostly
orchestral symphonic I tend to like that
because I like I like that sort of
dynamically complex it is and how you're
constantly shifting these patterns of
intelligibility in this very complex
evolving manner and and I like the long
form that's often found with classical
music but let's be honest because that's
what you guys deserve and I get by
really well on the desert island if I
had the Beatles and I could listen to
the music of the Beatles precisely
because there's something about the
music I mean obviously that dates me and
certain ways but in a lot of that music
you find a quite exemplary intersection
of poetry and some fairly powerful and
interesting melodic structure and so I
hope that answers the question that's
that's those are the yeah that's sort of
the the two genres I find myself
listening to most often one more thing
but it also depends like like so often
if I am doing spiritual practice I'd
like to put on sort of canticles being
sung or Japanese shakuhachi music
precisely because that music is
conducive towards enhancing getting into
you know a flow state and mindfulness
so I guess like many people it's on
somewhat eclectic and I tried to give
you sort of an overall overall hierarchy
Jonathan would be happy about that I
suppose ah
and the context in which different
genres gain different priority for me
thank you very much for that question
next question is from Steven as well
clarification for previous questions so
God doesn't actually have to be watching
the universe to keep it existing it's
just a helpful perspective also that's
the idea what's the one so um so there
are interpretation I mean you can even
see this in Platonists where he says
that everything is sort of contemplating
itself in some sense I I like other
people I think pearl and others resist
idealism in the modern post Cartesian
sense of the word interpretations of
latinas so yes I don't think if you mean
if you mean by God sorry this is that's
what everybody says when they talk about
God but what do you mean by God I mean
and that's that's all right so I take it
let's let's let's mean a standard sort
of classical theism what I mean by God
is an independently consciousness that
has something somehow I don't know how
analogous to our mental states and that
those mental states being in an
intentional relationship to reality
perceiving them like Berkeley would say
actually somehow keeps them in existence
if you mean if you ask me does that God
have to be there in order for the
universe to exist no I don't I don't
think so why because I'm generally
deeply critical of idealism as an
epistemological and metaphysical
position so ideal doesn't classically
has problems
you know what the
ancestry issue it has problems that I
need an independent argument a
non-circular independent argument for
God in order to posit God as a solution
to the ancestry problem so there's many
of these deep deep issues but if what
you mean by God is something more like
Spinoza's God which is right and what
Platina is probably meant by the news
right which is the set of all the
patterns of intelligibility and how they
like think it's something and something
that would be included through this but
not reduce to it put of all the current
laws of physics right oh these are all
the patterns of structural functional
organization right now and all and all
of sort of the ones that we're going to
discover and all the patterns that make
living things living things etc all the
patterns that make erosion erosion that
make evolution evolution all of that and
how do they are all right deeply deeply
interconnected and interdependent and
then the idea is that if what you mean
by God is that set that set of
properties and principles let's use
principles that set of principles that
totally constrains the probability
possibility space for all actual events
I guess something analogous also to
Wayne had then I get then I can sort of
see and and that's that's very much the
kind of God that Isaac that Einstein was
talking about he was very clearly and
explicitly invoking Spinoza is God then
I could see that now what's the one now
what's the one I think that's an echo so
for those of you who don't know this is
the ultimate entity in the Neoplatonic
system latinas for example and for for
platonist the one is not the pattern of
intelligibility but that which makes any
and all patterns of intelligibility
possible and and so the one isn't
anything you know it's in a strict sense
because it can't be an object
of thought because it is the source from
which all patterns of intelligence
belong together in an intelligible
fashion and I take it that what the one
is in a model such as mind is something
like the ground of being now the thing
about the ground of being is to say that
it's ideal is equally a mistake is to
say it's material because it's precisely
no thing at all it's the no thickness
because and this is something that I
think the especially the the Christian
neoplatonist made very clear right
though though that which grounds and
makes all understanding possible is not
something itself that we can understand
and so I take it that what the one would
be for me is an acknowledgment that
whatever ontology one has there is an
aspect to it that that is a no thingness
that it's and and thing doesn't just
mean please stop doing this some people
thing doesn't just mean a material body
many things are in Kippur oil in that
they are not body things like again like
like like like patterns of erosion they
happen to bodies and between bodies but
erosion itself isn't a body like because
it doesn't happen it's not locatable
what more one distinct specific local
spot in time and space England like
exists but in some and it's made up of
people that have bodies and objects that
have bodies and buildings that have
bodies but it itself isn't a body
because it's not it's not limited you
know to you know what do you mean when
you say England went to war with Germany
you know there's English people in
Germany and they're related to right
blah blah blah blah and all that sort of
stuff so the no thingness doesn't just
mean not a body it also means not a
process not a principle
not a law because all of those are
things that are objects of understanding
they we are all this is what I'm trying
to get at when I talk about there's
something in us that corresponds to this
that allows us to ultimately have a deep
conformity participatory knowing of the
one because there's an aspect of us
that's like that because the process of
framing is never something that is in my
frame and so that gives me something I
participate in that phenomenological
mystery that I can never make the
framing that makes my understanding
possible an object of my understanding I
can theoretically talk about it but I
can't bring it into something disclose
phenomenologically as an object for me
that gives me a participatory analog for
how every pattern of intelligibility is
ultimately depend on that with that
which is even saying that is a mistake
it's dependent on the ground by which
all things are intelligible which itself
is not anything that can be made
intelligible precisely because it is the
ground that makes things intelligible
that in my mind does not in any way
license any kind of idealism any kind of
dualism any kind of two world ism
because if you make any of those moves
you have ignored the argument that got
us here which is an argument for no
thingness and no thinness is no better
situated within idealism that it is
within materialism there is no there is
no inherent improvement by saying oh the
no thing this is a mental thing it's
still it's still a thing so I don't
think there's any inconsistency with
holding I'm non reductive physicalism
and holding something like the neo
platonic one because I don't think the
neo platonic one is consistent with any
physical ism or idealism or dualism
precisely because by its very nature it
transcends them all and it has to or
isn't the one
so I hope that for that that's a long
and complex argument I don't know what
that means for for some people's views
about God I'm just trying to answer the
question because it was directed towards
me and and and and how I try and get
these things consistent in my own
thinking all right next question is from
patreon supporter Steven last well Thank
You Steven
did your interest in spirituality
practices emerge from your study of
cognitive science or did your interest
in cognitive science result from your
personal spiritual disposition
chicken-or-egg the thing of course is
the the chicken and the egg the egg
creates the chicken we now know that so
we've got to come up with a better
metaphor right so that's a good question
I would say that Chris mr. Pietro said
this of me and because he's such an
insightful and dear friend I take it
very seriously he said that and give it
all and you have to you have to and he
knows everything else I just argued so
he's not denying any of what I've just
said but he said he said he thinks that
I'm some in some sense is a deeply
religious thinker and I think there's
truth to that in the sense that this
these questions about how to live deeply
how to live meaningfully what is self
transcendence well what is wisdom these
questions have I don't want to I don't I
don't want to I don't want to create a
romantic glorification of my own
autobiography i I've had a long-standing
affinity with them and I and I had
already gotten into philosophy and
encountered the dramatic transformative
figure of Socrates and then it had a
huge impact on me but then when I found
that that that pursuit of wisdom and
meaning and that exemplification of the
logos that I saw in Socrates was not
being carried out into academic
I then undertook spiritual practices
that did two things for me I think they
helped to develop that affinity and and
enable me to pursue more meaning and
wisdom and also they they gave me
practices by which I could try and carry
out the aspiration the aspirational
demand if that's the right word that I
found coming from my encounter with
Socrates and so as I was taking up these
practices I came to sort of an end of my
philosophical training and by that time
I had always been interested in
philosophy of mind and by that time the
but the practices had moved me to a
place and the academic world was
changing and cognitive science was
emerging and I went into cognitive
science from that sort of emerging I
don't like to sort of it spirituality
and some of the philosophical work that
I had read surrounding it from Taoist
and
Buddhist traditions and I found as I've
mentioned before that other people were
already trying to draw these things
together so I hope that answers your
question
now it's very much now like this that
the spirituality in the cognitive
science are constantly doing this
reciprocal beacon structuring and
restructuring of each other I couldn't I
couldn't make any clear division between
them now and how things unfold for me so
I'd like to make an announcement I'd
like to thank I thank you to all the
patreon subscribers and your support is
crucial to continuing to produce these
videos and for supporting the science
we're doing to try to find solutions to
the mean crisis we're going to shift a
lot of questions from the chat and
please identify yourself as a patron
subscriber to receive priority for your
questions
so the last question is now coming up
right thank you
I've got such a great team here I could
not do this without tongue so so so so
lucky
here's a question from Lowell Union
you've talked about wonder and emotion
being essential to rationality and how
we must find that place that puts us in
the flow state to get our goals done how
do you do that that's a great question
so the the flow State
I practice Tai Chi Chuan which which is
a Taoist practice and related practices
for gin cheek on each one j-john whole
family of practices and they're very
powerful for as I said they put me into
a frame of processing that allows me to
you know exact balance machinery and
coordination machinery into my cognition
and they they're you know Taoism as I
keep saying is the religion and no flow
it's the religion for getting you to get
in the flow state and exact it into your
cognition exact it into your existential
mode so it permeates your life as a
whole though I I practice also a
scientist the past now as I mentioned a
mindfulness practice and Metta
contemplation I also do a Neoplatonic
practice of theoria which is basically
trying to do what I described earlier
sort of move through these you know
these agent arena relationships between
patterns of cognition and levels of
reality that are in a co determined
fashion usually disclosing you of each
other in an acog a and I move and I go
through an Anna gaga ascent and I've
been helped by that both from the pagan
neo platonic tradition and also many
practices from the Christian neo
platonic tradition and that is very
colorful for inducing in me wonder and
at times aw and and I'm going to make
this argument
in some of the episodes that are coming
and I'm gonna try and make it a tighter
argument that you know this brings about
what I was talking about earlier
engenders aspiration in me and what
Agnes colored costs calls aspiration and
part of the argument that I've made and
some of you might have seen a talk I
made for this talk on acts in Toronto
the aspiration to rationality has to be
part of rationality because if and
here's here's to go back again circling
back here's one of the issues I have
with people who try to reduce
rationality to logical argumentation as
I've tried to show making use of la
Paul's work and Agnes Keller it's worth
you can't go through qualitative
development transformational experience
aspiration in in an inferential manner
there's deep reasons why that doesn't
work and so the processes by which you
go through aspiration are not
inferential argumentative processes if
you reduce notice my language if you
reduce rationality to inferential
argumentation then you have to say that
the process of aspiring for rationality
is not itself a rational process which
means there is no rational justification
for the aspiration to rationality and
then react with rationality becomes a
self undermining self-destroying entity
the at and this is this is this is the
core of coloureds argument the
aspiration to rationality has itself to
be a kind on a constituent of
rationality and what I find is that
these practices are not only conducive
of the Wonder and conduces of the
cognitive flexibility and the insight
that is important for rationalize they
help engender and me the aspiration
towards rationality and ultimately
towards the wisdom that I've just argued
is central to rationality into wisdom
now I've made that argument in brief I
made it a little bit more detail on the
that I made on the silicon talk the view
from above it's it's on my channel if
you want to watch it also this argument
is going to come back and develop be
developed in depth when I talk about
theories of wisdom and aspiration and
the divine double so there's more
argument and coming to bear about this
but that's sort of the gist of it right
now so here's a question from Twitter
from Colin Donald won our dogs
continuously in a kind of flow state
could all animals be enlightened in that
sense okay so first of all the question
between the two the connection between
the two questions I don't the quate
enlightenment with being in the flow
state as I tried to argue I think
enlightenment is a complex dynamical
system of consciousness and cognition
that reliably and systematically
addresses the perennial problems I think
the flow state only addresses one aspect
of that which I call the problem of the
of the reflectiveness gap I think you
need many other features within your
cognition to be enlightened because in
the end I think enlightenment as I said
is probably only appropriate for
creatures who like us seem to be able to
get into existential right modal
confusion or seem to be capable of
bullshitting ourselves in a
comprehensive and culturally magnified
fashion right I don't I don't know but I
don't have reason to believe that dogs
right ever experience sort of something
like the existential project that human
being said I mean I'm gonna talk about
this later
you know Heidegger famously said we are
the beings who's right whose being is in
question
we don't come with sort of a ready-made
being it is something and I'm gonna I'm
using this word deliberately it is
something we aspire to this
is why I'm so critical of people who
think you are born with your true self I
don't think we are those kinds of being
I think dogs might be but I don't think
we are so you don't see a dog sort of
like the what is it to be a dog like how
can I be a good dog like am I feeling am
i living up to my dog nurse I mean dogs
don't don't get me wrong dogs can suffer
pain I think they can suffer grief and
I'm not trivializing any of that but did
they do they fall into those kinds of
issues that bespeak that we face the
perennial problems so I don't think so
and for that reason because I think it's
reasonable to conclude although by no
means certain that they don't face the
perennial problems the way we do that
that they aren't in enlightenment they
don't have enlightenment I don't even
think dogs are perpetually in the flow
state because you need a balance between
sort of challenge and skills and dogs
spend a lot of their days just sleeping
and lazing about when in situations that
don't seem highly challenging to them so
that's a really fun question and I
enjoyed it so thank you very much we
have time for another question this is
from a patreon supporter Quist
crystalline river and thank you very
much for your support I would be really
curious to hear your thoughts on Joseph
Campbell's work and his ideas on
following your bliss as it relates to
individual purpose and complicit
consistent flow state insight cascade so
first of all to give credit where credit
is due because I think this is always
important I'm encountering Joseph
Campbell's the power of myth especially
first did the show with the interview
with Bill Moyers had a huge influence on
me as I said my first philosopher is
Plato and my first psychologist is Jung
I met young through the work of
Robertson Davies v business and then
very shortly thereafter you know Joseph
Campbell of the Moyers thing and that
had a really profound impact on me I
going to vote one of the so the four
final lectures of the series the series
is all filmed by the way the guys but
the four final lectures dealing with
like the five prophets of so I finished
my argument and then I put it into
dialogue with people like Heidegger
Tillich Corbin Barfield and Yonge and so
there's gonna be a discussion there and
so I think that what Kant I mean there's
a there's a sense in which I think
Jordan Peterson is sort of our time
periods
Joseph Campbell in that what Joseph
Campbell did was he brought young back
made it accessible made it relevant got
people to see how there might be value
to young now of course I think there's
criticisms of that because there wasn't
much criticism and there is a lot of
criticism of the Union framework that
should be heard and should be addressed
and should be responded to as there is
of any important and profound framework
but nevertheless I think you know camels
ideas really really did he was a great
teacher and that he made Jung's ideas
intelligible and accessible and I've
gotten of itself is of great importance
it had a huge impact on me it really
opened me up to a deeper exploration of
symbolism and of metaphor and of altered
states of consciousness dream states etc
so very important impact on me continual
I keep my guy I go back to this time and
time again I'm not sure I'm not quite
clear about following your bliss part of
it I've seen you say that in in various
instances and product part of my
hesitancy is I'm not quite sure where
that means if it if it means something
like a sense that one is on a path in
which wisdom and virtue are
reliably not perfectly and not
completely and and I'm not trying to say
anything premature but are being
cultivated of being realized in by other
people with respect to you not your own
self identification or self label but if
other people are saying hey that was
really insightful or that was very
helpful or that was a wise thing or that
was a really brave or very honest thing
if that's if that is becoming more and
more what's happening in that what's
following your bliss means that I I
think that's right I just don't know I
I'm just uncomfortable with the word
bliss as describing that because that's
I don't experience that in my in myself
or the people that I'm talking to you
they don't seem to reported as being a
blissful state of bliss means kind of a
pain a sort of an ecstasy or
overwhelming kind of joy that's going on
I think that if it if it and I've heard
some people interpreted it this way if
it means sort of trust your gut in the
sense that deep down you always know
what the right thing to do is I think
that's absolute in this sorry
this is alright I don't mean to get
angry and I'm not attributing this as a
person who asked the question I want to
make clear about that we've got to stop
trying to find the divine part of
ourselves what I mean by that the
faculty that is perfect and will never
mislead us and and we got it just like
we have to stop demonizing your
perception can mislead you your thinking
can mislead you your intuition can
mislead you your dreams can mislead you
your emotions can mislead you your there
is no place this is this is this is part
of the you know the first noble truth
there is no place that is safe from the
threat of self-deception there's no
place in the world there's no place in
yourself you do not have a secret
angelic faculty that if you just get in
touch with it and Trust it it will lead
you securely because there is no part of
you that has that capacity
there's no evidence for it and we have
massive evidence that every one of the
faculties I've named lots of good
empirical evidence can be reliable
sources of self deceptive
self-destructive behavior if that's what
people mean and I'm not sure that
Campbell meant that I'm being very
careful here not to attribute this to
Campbell but I've heard some people
interpret follow your bliss to me not
and that's something that I'm deeply
deeply critical oh that's something a
deeply critical of because it gets us
its warts one of the things I argue we
really need which is to read to
reconnect with our participatory knowing
the process by which we know things by
coming to identify with them whereby our
self-knowledge and our knowledge of the
thing are deeply intertwined and
intermesh and Inter afforded but if we
if we have mistaken deeply mistaken ways
in which we're identifying with
ourselves that part of me is the angelic
pearl pure part then it directly deeply
thwarts an appropriate relationship of
participatory knowing that we need in
order to respond to the meaning crisis
so that's why I'm deeply deeply critical
of it I'm sorry if I caught a little bit
hot under the collar but this is this is
one of the things that I think is
pervasive in the culture it needs to be
given some rather sort of stringent
criticism so I fear that once again
we've come to the end of our time one
more time I want to thank all the
support I want to give a special shout
out and thank you to all the patreon
supporters thank you for for your
support thank you for your courage and
thank you for everybody like the people
who you know are tweeting me questions
the people who are making comments
please remember again and some of you
are emailing me right and some of you
are emailing along among things that I
can't respond to everything I literally
can't I did like it's not possible but I
want to know that I want you to know
that it's it's very appreciative and and
again I deeply mean this given Who I am
and my own sort of idiosyncratic
psychological profile that's kind of
incur
and the critical in a constructive sense
interaction I find deeply encouraging
thank you all very much everyone and I
look forward to seeing many of you again
Oh a month from now thank you very much
how's that